Guide to the First Unitarian Congregational Society of Brooklyn records ARC.109
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 2: Subject Files., 1790-1980; 4.75 Linear Feet In 10 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box.
  Of particular note are the "History" files which contain documents related to the early formation of the Congregation. These files include correspondence between the founders, resolutions and other actions of Trustees, early lists of subscribers, By-Laws, and early bills and accounts. The documents address the incorporation of the Congregation, the acquisition of land and the building of the Church of the Saviour, ministers, music, and other major matters of the congregation. Documents related to the early formation of the 2nd Congregation can also be found among these "History" folders. Some other documents related to the early and foundational years of the church can be found in the folders on By-Laws, Covenants and Statements of Faith, and Special Services. Also of interest are documents on the Church's work with children and youth including various clubs and very early documents regarding the Church's Sunday School. There is also club work here regarding psychiatric social work and counseling made available to parishioners during the tenure of John H. Lathrop. Researchers interested in the Low family should also note one file regarding the family with documents mostly unrelated to the church dating back to 1790.
  Subject Files also holds published directories of the Church which have Parish lists, club reports with member rolls, updated by-laws and other information on the Church. Some of these directories have been annotated, particularly in the Parish membership lists. Other family-oriented documents include the Bequests, Memorials, Special Services, and membership files.
  - Bequests: A-L, 1847-1941 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bequests: M-Z, 1875-1940 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bequests: Memorial Lanterns, 1916-1918 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bequests: Miscellaneous, 1883-1942 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bequests: Murals, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Bequests: Parker Memorial Mosaic, 1934-1935 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn Liberal Christian Union, 1866, 1888 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - The Brooklyn Unitarian, 1959, 1970, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - By-Laws, 1845, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Celebrations: Anniversaries, General, 1916-1944, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Celebrations: 50th Anniversary, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Celebrations: 75th Anniversary, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Celebrations: 100th Anniversary, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Celebrations: Channing Centenary, 1880 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Celebrations: Lathrop's 20th Anniversary, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Celebrations: Lathrop's 25th Anniversary, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Celebrations: Lathrop's 25th Anniversary: Dinner and Reception, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Celebrations: Lathrop's 25th Anniversary: Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Celebrations: Other Congregations, 1914-1937 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Celebrations: Unitarian Festival, 1862 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cemetery: Greenwood, 1844-1929, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Moved to Oversize Box 1:
    - One map of plots with subscriber names (Undated)
    - Two ledger pages of Treasurer's reports of cemetery accounts(1845, 1846)
  - Cemetery: Greenwood: Correspondence, 1901-1941 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Clergyman's Office Year Book, 1956-1957 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Clerk of the Church, 1927-1932 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Clipper Ship Drawings, 1847-1852 (Box OS-4)
  - Clubs: Alfred T. White Society, 1931, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Clubs: Boy Scouts, 1925-1941 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Clubs: General Entertainments and Ideas for Entertainments, Undated, 1914, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Clubs: Laymen's League, 1921-1925 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Clubs: Miscellaneous, 1916-1939, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Clubs: Old Fort Club, 1923-1931 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Clubs: Old Fort Club: Scrapbook, 1922-1924 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Clubs: Pierrepont Wednesday Club, 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Clubs: Psychiatric Social Work, Beatrice Bishop Berle, 1930-1931 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Clubs: Samuel Longfellow Club, Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Clubs: Service Men's Center, 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Clubs: Young People's Religious Union, 1923-1937 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Communion, Undated, 1914 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Covenants and Statements of Faith, Undated, 1842-1844, 1920s (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Deacons, 1913-1937 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Directories, 1890-1891, 1914-1921 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Directories, 1922-1930 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Directories, 1930s (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Directories, 1942-1950 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Directories, 1953, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - History, 1830s-1843 (Box 14, Folder 5-7)
  - History, 1844-1960s (Box 15, Folder 1-10)
    One "Deed of Land" for Church of the Saviour plot, 1844
  - History: Bills, Receipts and Accounts, 1842-1851 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - History: Studies and Pamphlets, 1920, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - History: Timelines, Undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - In Memoriam, circa 1880s, 1912-1953 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - In Memoriam: World War I, Honor Roll and Service Flag, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - In Memoriam: World War I, Honor Roll and Tablet in Vestibule, 1923-1924 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - In Memoriam: World War II, 1940s (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Inventories of Church Files, circa 1930s (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Legal Issues, 1848, 1910, 1927-1931 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Low Family Papers, 1790, 1813-1880s, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Membership: Attendance, 1920s (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Membership: Transfer by letter, 1890s-1920s (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Membership Drive, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Music, 1900-1950 (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
  - Organ, 1848, 1900-1927 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Organ: Repairs and Contracts, 1900-1945 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Post Office Mission Books, 1921, 1923-1928 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Post Office Mission: Strike Notice, 1936 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1929-1967 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Programs: other Churches and Services, Undated, 1855-1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Publicity, 1910s-1940s (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Resolutions, 1910s-1940s (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - The Retreat, Inc., 1910s-1930s (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - The Samaritan Alliance, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Signature File, 1920s-1940 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Special Services, 1844, 1860s-1940s (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Staff, 1920s-1930s (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Sunday School, 1842-1873 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Sunday School: Christmas and Easter Services, 1868-1919 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Survey and Recommendations, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Union Services, 1910s-1930s (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Visitors Log Book, 1925-1949 (Box 19, Item 1)
  - Visitors Log Book, 1949-1963 (Box 19, Item 2)
  - White, Alfred T.: Obituaries, Memorials, and Condolences, 1921-1941 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - White, Frances Harriet, Undated, 1937 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Oversize Flat Box 1 (Box OS 1, Folder -)
- Series 3: Ministers., 1834-1967; 1 Linear Feet In 2 manuscript boxes.
  Folders are arranged by minister in chronological order of tenure. Because several files in the series relate to John Lathrop, these are divided and arranged alphabetically.
  The Ministers series contains files kept regarding the installation, resignation, and other major matters for the ministers of the Church of the Saviour. The materials are primarily correspondence and copies of resolutions and votes of the Society on these matters. Some files also include sermons, relevant news clippings, and articles. The file on Frederick W. Holland has correspondence regarding protest and controversy over his leadership during a developing schism in the Church as well as his record of funerals, baptisms, and marriages in the Church during his tenure. Clippings and Orders of Service related to Alfred E. Goodnough, H. Price Collier, and Samuel A. Eliot can be found in the Scrapbooks series. Additional sermons by H. Price Collier can also be found in the Scrapbooks series.
  In the case of John Lathrop there are several folders due to the bulk of material. These are broken up by subject including his installation, committees he was involved with, other churches he communicated with, and memorial services after his death. Some of the committees here include the the League of Nations Association, the Long Island Historical Society, the Religious Arts Guild, refugee aid associations and other organizations dealing with ecumenical issues, the peace movement, and welfare and aid to the needy. While these files relate to what the Church kept in regards to Lathrop, for documents related to Lathrop's work, including his sermons, see the John H. Lathrop Files series.
  - D.H. Barlow (1834-1837), 1834-1837, 1937, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Frederick W. Holland (1838-1841), 1838-1846, 1894 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    One item moved to Oversize Box 1:
    Council meeting of several churches. Includes note "Ralph W. Emerson was present"
  - Frederick A. Farley (1842-1863), 1841-1892 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Alfred P. Putnam (1864-1886), 1864-1880s, 1905-1906 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Alfred E. Goodnough (1887-1888), 1887-1888, 1949 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - H. Price Collier (1888-1893), 1888-1893, 1942 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Samuel A. Eliot (1893-1897), 1892-1897, 1907, 1942-1957 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - John P. Forbes (1898-1910) (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Boards and Committees, Educational and Cultural, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Boards and Committees, religious groups, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Boards and Committees, social service and welfare organizations, 1930s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Installation, 1911, 1930s (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Installation correspondence, 1900-1920s (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): International organizations and world alliances, 1910s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Memorial Services (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - John H. Lathrop (1911-1967): Other Churches, correspondence and programs, 1920s-1940s (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Ministers Assistants, 1890s-1930s (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Oversize Flat Box 1 (Box OS 1, Folder -)
- Series 4: John H. Lathrop Files., 1849-1960; 11.5 Linear Feet In 27 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box.
  The John H. Lathrop Files are arranged alphabetically by subject and material type.
  The John H. Lathrop Files series contains the working and reference files of John H. Lathrop who served as minister to the First Unitarian Congregation of Brooklyn from 1911 to 1967. The series covers Lathrop's varied interests and prolific work. Lathrop's work within the Church and community can be seen through his sermons, correspondence, parishioners' files, and work with organizations like the Brooklyn Urban League which he helped found and managed as president for many years. As minister for the Church during both world wars, Lathrop was interested in the international peace movement. Lathrop was involved with various organizations which mobilized for peace like the War Resisters League, the Emergency Peace Campaign, and the National Peace Conference, which he headed. Lathrop was similarly interested in international aid and outreach and had files pertaining to humanitarian efforts in Germany, Spain, Hungary and other nations.
  There are some records within this series regarding the First Church's connection to Unitarians in Transylvania and their church there. Several files also address Czechoslovakia and the Unitarian Service Committee trip there which Lathrop was a part of. The First Unitarian Congregation of Brooklyn had a special connection to Czechoslovakia as a former member of the Church, Charlotte Garrigue, had married the first president of Czechoslovakia, Tomas Garrigue Masaryk. Lathrop kept up correspondence with their daughter, Alice Garrigue Masaryk, one of the founders of the Czechoslovak Red Cross, and their son, Jan Masaryk, the Foreign Minister of Czechoslovakia.
  The series also contains a collection of reference material on various topics of interest to Lathrop including marriage, peace, labor and unemployment, religious freedom, liberal Christianity, and other related issues. These reference files consist of articles, pamphlets, and various materials from organizations Lathrop was interested in or with which he was tangentially involved. Lathrop's sermons deal with this broad range of topics as well, particularly ideas of liberal Christianity and its application in the world. Lathrop's work with like-minded organizations like the International Association for Liberal Christianity and Religious Freedom and the American Committee on Religious Rights and Minorities can be found in this series.
  Some files on Lathrop and documents created by him can be found in many other series within the collection, but particularly within the Ministers series which contains documents on his installation, organizations he served on the board of, and memorial services for his death.
  - Altar of All Faiths: Brahmo Samaj plaque, artist's sketch, Undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - American Committee on Religious Rights and Minorities, 1928-1944, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 2-5)
  - American League for Human Rights, 1933 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - American Legion, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Includes signed letter from U.S. Senator Royal S. Copeland.
  - American Red Cross, Brooklyn Chapter, 1921-1943 (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
  - American Unitarian Association, 1919, 1933-1938 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Arab National League, 1937-1947 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Articles (by Lathrop), 1930s-1940s (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Berkeley Unitarian Church, 1906-1911 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Bhagavat Gita, Order of 80 Certificate, 1899 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Bible Studies, 1904, circa 1910s-1940s (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Book Reviews, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - British Unitarianism, circa 1940s (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Brooklyn Interorganizational Council on Disarmament, 1931-1934 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Brooklyn Urban League, 1931-1939 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Channing, William, 1937-1938 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1920s-1930s (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Abraham Lincoln's Assassination, 1865 (Box OS 2, Folder 2)
  - Civic Committee for Adult Literacy, 1932-1935 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Committee for World Disarmament and World Reconstruction, 1951-1952 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: A, 1912-1944 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: B, 1900s-1950s (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Babel, Henry, 1955 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    Includes two letters from Adlai Stevenson.
  - Correspondence: Brooklyn Ministers, circa 1910s-1930s (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: C-D, 1910s-1940s (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: E-F, 1910s-1940s (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Family, 1849-1912 (Box 24, Folder 10-12)
  - Correspondence: Family, 1913-1945 (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence: G-H, 1910s-1940s (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: I-L, 1910s-1940s (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: M-N, 1910s-1930s (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Niebuhr, H. Richard, 1937 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: O-P, 1910s-1940s (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: R, 1910s-1940s (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: S-Z, 1910s-1940s (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Taft, William H., 1921 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1928-1952 (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
  - Czechoslovakia: American Relief for Czechoslovakia, Inc., 1947-1949 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Czechoslovakia: Correspondence, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Czechoslovakia: Endicott, NY, 1951-1953 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Czechoslovakia: Masaryk, Alice Garrigue, 1933-1953 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Czechoslovakia: Masaryk, Jan, 1940s (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Czechoslovakia: Masaryk family, 1939-1948 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Czechoslovakia: Olesovice Children's Home`, 1946-1948 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Czechoslovakia: Unitarian Service Committee Trip, 1946-1947 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    Moved to Oversize Box 3:
    - One large sign in Czech for a sermon given by Dr. Lathrop, 1947.
    - One small sign for the Unitarian Service Committee Medical Teaching Mission, Undated.
  - Czechoslovakia: Unitarian Service Committee Trip: Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Czechoslovakia: Unitarian Service Committee Trip: Correspondence, 1946 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Czechoslovakia: Unitarian Service Committee Trip: Personal Report of John Lathrop, circa 1946 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Dresser, Horatio, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Dresser, Horatio: The Quimby Manuscripts, 1903, circa 1920s, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Eastman, Rebecca Hooper, circa 1937 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Emergency Peace Campaign, 1936-1937 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Field, Noel, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Free Church Fellowship, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - German Churches, 1947-1948 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Germany: Relief for German Children, 1924 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Greece, 1928-1930, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Haspl, Karel, 1952-1953 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Hosmer, Fred: Portrait and Pension Fund, 1920-1925 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Hungary and Transylvania, 1920s-1940s (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Hungary: Gabor, Gelei, 1940s (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Hungary: Kossuth (including copies of articles from 1860's-1880's), circa 1930s-1940s (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Hungary: Siklossy, Laszlo, 1924-1934 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - India, 1935-1938, 1954 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - International Association for Liberal Christianity and Religious Freedom (IARF), 1929-1941 (Box 28, Folder 16-17)
  - IARF, 1946-1954 (Box 29, Folder 1-5)
  - IARF: Amsterdam, 1948-1949 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - IARF: Berne, 1946-1948 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - IARF: Lathrop Articles re:, 1940s-1950s (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - IARF: Society of Friends, 1948-1949 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - International Religious Fellowship, 1946-1948 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Islam, 1936, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Japan, 1926-1929 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Journals and Accounts of European Trips, 1900, 1902 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Kagawa, Toyohiko, 1935-1936 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Krakes, Pavel, 1948-1953 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - League of Nations, 1925-1926 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Lectures, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - The Living Faith of A Unitarian, 1944 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - The Living Faith of a Unitarian: Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Mayor of Brooklyn Heights (Brooklyn Heights Press), 1941 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Melish, Dr. Howard, 1931-1944 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Mexico, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Mita, Edo, 1953 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - National Consumers' League Conference, 1932-1933 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - National Peace Conference, 1935-1937 (Box 31, Folder 6-8)
  - National Peace Conference, 1938-1940 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - National Peace Conference, 1941-1942 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - New York University, 1932 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, Undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 33, Folder 4-6)
  - Notes, circa 1930s (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Obituaries, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Other Churches: Programs, 1901-1945 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Parishioners Files: A-D, 1931-1936 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Parishioners Files: E-J, 1931-1936 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Parishioners Files: K-M, 1931-1936 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Parishioners Files: N-R, 1931-1936 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Parishioners Files: S-Z, 1931-1936 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Parishioners Lists, circa 1910s-1940s (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Petitions, Letters, and Resolutions Signed, 1950s (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Philippines, 1940s-1950s (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Pioli, Giovanni, circa 1950s (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Poems, collected, circa 1910s-1950s (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Prayers, circa 1910s-1940s (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Prayers, collected, circa 1900s-1940s (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Quotations, collected, circa 1900s-1940s (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Quotations and Music, collected, 1910s-1940s (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Reference: Czechoslovakia, 1940s (Box 36, Folder 2-3)
  - Reference: Eastern Europe (collected and bound articles), 1910s-1920s (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Reference: Eastern Europe, collected and bound articles, 1910s-1930s (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Reference: Health and Hygiene, 1930-1941 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Reference: Labor and Unemployment, 1930s-1940s (Box 37, Folder 3-4)
  - Reference: Liberalism and Related Causes, 1930s-1940s (Box 38, Folder 1-3)
  - Reference: Marriage, Birth Control and Family Counseling, 1920s-1940s (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Reference: Marriage, Birth Control, and Family Counseling, 1920s-1940s (Box 39, Folder 1-2)
  - Reference: Peace and Foreign Policy, 1920s-1940s (Box 39, Folder 3-6)
  - Reference: Peace and Foreign Policy, 1920s-1940s (Box 40, Folder 1-5)
  - Reference: Peace and Foreign Policy, 1920s-1940s (Box 41, Folder 1-4)
  - Reference: Peace and Foreign Policy, 1920s-1940s (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Reference: Theology and Philosophy, 1920s-1940s (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Reference: Unitarianism, 1900 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Second Unitarian Church, 1913 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Sermons and Orders of Worship, Undated, 1914-1932 (Box 43, Folder 1-7)
  - Sermons and Orders of Worship, 1933-1936 (Box 44, Folder 1-4)
  - Sermons and Orders of Worship, 1937-1943 (Box 45, Folder 1-6)
  - Sermons and Orders of Worship, 1944-1951 (Box 46, Folder 1-4)
  - Sermons, published, 1940s-1950s (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Sermons: Radio Address, 1925-1936 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Sermons, repeated (1 of 2), 1909-1936 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Sermons, repeated (2 of 2), 1909-1939 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Sixth Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion, 1945 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Sixth Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion: Papers Presented, 1945 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Spanish Refugee Appeal, 1945-1950 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Student Christian Movement in New England, 1937 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Theological Schools and Courses, circa 1900s-1940s (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Transylvania: Csiki, Gabrielic, 1922-1923, 1934, 1938 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Unitarian Festival, 1942 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - UNESCO, 1950-1952 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Unity Church: Directory, circa 1910s, 1947 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Universitat Jena, 1902 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, 1901 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Vit, Karl V., 1948-1952 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Wald, Lillian, 1932-1934, 1940 (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - White, Alfred T., 1912-1919 (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - World Churches, 1920s-1940s (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - World's Fair, Temple of Religion, 1937-1939 (Box 48, Folder 12)
  - Oversize Flat Box 3 (Box OS 3, Folder -)
- Series 5: Unitarian Movement Files., 1850-1975; 1850-1945; 1 Linear Feet In 2 manuscript boxes.
  The Unitarian Movement Files are arranged alphabetically by subject and material type.
  The Unitarian Movement Files contain the general files kept by the Church on its involvement with the Unitarian movement across America, primarily through the American Unitarian Association (AUA), and in other parts of the world. The AUA material concerns Unitarian outreach, publicity, and social-service. There is one folder related to the congregation's sister church in Transylvania. For more on the Church's efforts abroad, see the John H. Lathrop Files for papers on Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Transylvania, and the Philippines.
  - American Unitarian Association (AUA): Aided Churches, 1928-1932 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - AUA: Administration: Officers and General Procedures, 1927-1933 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - AUA: Alliance Manuals and Pamphlets, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 49, Folder 3)